# AdamH.Sparks

Plant Disease Management Specialist@IRRI

**International Rice Research Institute (IRRI)** 

#### skills

GIS

modelling agricultural statistics

### contact

IRRI

Los Baños, Laguna Philippines

> Mail: DAPO Box 7777 Metro Manila 1301 Philippines

a.sparks@irri.org

+63 (2) 580 5600 **\**+63 908 182 8012 □
adam.h.sparks **⑤** 

### web

+AdamHSparksPhD **3**@adamhsparks

adamhsparks (?)

### personal summary

I am a plant pathology epidemiologist and ecologist who can effectively communicate and collaborate with diverse partners and stakeholders in an international setting. My work encompases traditional field-based research, epidemiological modeling, climate change, GIS and statistical methods. In turn, I use this work to understand what drives crop disease epidemics and derive disease control recomendations farmers and make recomendations for policy makers and other decision makers.

Scientist I

# experience

since 2012

	Develop tools and strategies for farmers to use in addressing rice diseases	
2011-2012	International Rice Research Institute (IRRI) Linked plant disease models with GIS tools	Post-Doctoral Fellow
2009-2010	<b>Kansas State University</b> Post-Doctoral Research Associate Developed and refined predictive Fusarium head blight models for wheat	
2002-2004	University of Nebraska-Lincoln Managed maize and soybean plant pathology exte	Research Technologist ension field research
2000-2003	University of Nebraska-Lincoln Managed maize and sorghum plant pathology ext	Research Technician ension field research
1999-2000	<b>Purdue University</b> Coordinated training events for Purdue Diagnostic	Assistant Director Training and Research Center
1997-1999	Purdue University  Managed soybean and canola production research	Research Technician h studies

### education

2009	<b>Ph.D.</b> Plant Pathology Plant Disease Epidemiology and Ecology	Kansas State University, Manhattan, KS	
	<b>Dissertation:</b> Disease risk mapping with metamodels for coarse resolution predictors: global potato late blight risk now and under future climate conditions		
2007	<b>Graduate Certificate</b> Geography Geographic Information Science	Kansas State University, Manhattan, KS	
2000	<b>B.Sc.</b> Agronomy Soil and Crop Management	Purdue University, West Lafayette, IN	

# **publications**

### peer-reviewed

Climate change may have limited effect on global risk of potato late blight A H Sparks, G A Forbes, R J Hijmans, K A Garrett

Global Change Biology (2014). DOI: 10.1111/gcb.12587

# A review on crop losses, epidemiology and disease management of rice brown spot to identify research priorities and knowledge gaps

M K Barnwal, A Kotasthane, N Magculia, P K Mukherjee, S Savary, A K Sharma, H B Singh, U S Singh, A H Sparks, M Variar, N Zaidi

European Journal of Plant Pathology 136.3 (2013) pp. 443-457. DOI: 10.1007/s10658-013-0195-6

#### Taking transgenic rice drought screening to the field.

A C M Gaudin, A Henry, A H Sparks, I H Slamet-Loedin

Journal of Experimental Botany 63.2 (2012) pp. 695-709. DOI: 10.1093/jxb/ers313

# An Economic Assessment of the Impact of Mango Pulp Weevil on the Agricultural Sector of Palawan, Philippines

J D Mckinley, A H Sparks, V O Pede, B Duff

The Philippine Agricultural Scientist 95.3 (2012) pp. 286-292

# Complexity in climate-change impacts: an analytical framework for effects mediated by plant disease

K A Garrett, G A Forbes, S Savary, P Skelsey, A H Sparks, C Valdivia, A H C van Bruggen, L Willocquet, A Djurle, E Duveiller, H Eckersten, S Pande, C Vera Cruz, J Yuen

Plant Pathology 60.1 (2011) pp. 15-30. DOI: 10.1111/j.1365-3059.2010.02409.x

# International agricultural research tackling the effects of global and climate changes on plant diseases in the developing world

S Savary, A Nelson, A H Sparks, L Willocquet, E Duveiller, G Mahuku, G Forbes, K A Garrett, J Padgham, S Pande, M Sharma, J Yuen, A Djurle

Plant Disease 48 (2011) pp. 1-40

# A metamodeling framework for extending the application domain of process-based ecological models

A H Sparks, G A Forbes, R J Hijmans, K A Garrett

Ecosphere 2.8 (2011) art90. DOI: 10.1890/ES11-00128.1

#### Beyond yield: plant disease in the context of ecosystem services.

M R Cheatham, M N Rouse, P D Esker, S Ignacio, W Pradel, R Raymundo, A H Sparks, G A Forbes, T R Gordon, K A Garrett

Phytopathology 99.11 (2009) pp. 1228–36. DOI: 10.1094/PHYT0-99-11-1228

#### Ecology and epidemiology in R: disease forecasting

P D Esker, A H Sparks, L Campbell, Z Guo, M Rouse, S D Silwal, S Tolos, B Van Allen, K A Garrett The Plant Health Instructor (2008)

#### Ecology and epidemiology in R: modeling plant disease progress over time

A H Sparks, P D Esker, M Bates, W Dall'Acqua, Z Guo, V Segovia, S D Silwal, S Tolos, K A Garrett (2008)

#### Ecology and epidemiology in R: spatial analysis

A H Sparks, P D Esker, G Antony, L Campbell, E E Frank, L Huebel, M N Rouse, B Van Allen, K A Garrett

The Plant Health Instructor (2008)

#### Introduction to the R programming environment

K A Garrett, P D Esker, A H Sparks

The Plant Health Instructor (2007)

#### Ecology and epidemiology in R: modeling dispersal gradients

P D Esker, A H Sparks, G Antony, M Bates, W Dall'Acqua, E E Frank, L Huebel, V Segovia, K A Garrett The Plant Health Instructor (2007)

#### Writing teaching documents as a class project

K A Garrett, P D Esker, A H Sparks, L C Scharmann

The Plant Health Instructor (2007)

# conferences/proceedings

#### Modeling the impact of disease resistance on rice yields in the Philippines and Indonesia

A H Sparks, J Anaurio, C Duku, M Noel, D Raitzer

In Proceedings of the Australasian Plant Pathology Society 2013 Meeting (2013)

#### Preventing what ails rice with a strategic, statistical, prescriptive model system

A H Sparks, S Savary, A Nelson

Phytopathology vol. 102:S4.113.7 (2012)

#### Predisposition factors affecting brown spot disease development in rice

N F Magculia, A H Sparks

Phytopathology vol. 102:S4.74.7 (2012)

#### Putting information to use: Decisions at different scales

S Savary, A H Sparks, N Nelson, N McRoberts, P D Esker

Phytopathology vol. 102:S4.162 (2012)

# An economic assessment of the impact of mango pulp weevil on the agricultural sector of Palawan, Philippines

J McKinley, V O Pede, A H Sparks, B Duff

The Conference Secretariat, 2011 PAEDA Biennial Convention (2011)

#### Income inequality and economic growth in the Philippines

G B Ballesefin, V O Pede, A H Sparks

The Conference Secretariat, 2011 PAEDA Biennial Convention (2011)

#### Crop losses in highly populated areas: A global perspective

L Willocquet, A Nelson, A Sparks, A Laborte, S Savary

Phytopathology vol. 101:S223 (2011)

#### Metamodels for scaling potato late blight risk analysis in climate change scenarios

A H Sparks, G Forbes, R Hijmans, K Garrett

Phytopathology vol. 100:S121 (2010)

#### Anticipating and responding to biological complexity in the effects of climate change on agriculture

K Garrett, G Forbes, S Pande, S Savary, A Sparks, C Valdivia, C Vera Cruz, L Willocquet IOP Conference Series: Earth and Environmental Science vol. 6.37 (2009)

### Adapting disease forecasting models to coarser scales: Global potato late blight prediction

A H Sparks, G Forbes, K A Garrett

Phytopathology vol. 99:S122 (2009)

#### Adapting global disease forecasting models for readily available weather data sets in GIS

A H Sparks, K A Garrett, G A Forbes

In Proceedings of the 10th International Epidemiology Workshop (2009). Geneva, NY, USA

# Regional predictions of potato late blight risk in a GIS incorporating disease resistance profiles, climate change, and risk neighborhoods

A H Sparks, R Raymundo, R Simon, G Forbes, K A Garrett

Phytopathology vol. 98:S149 (2008)

# book chapters

#### Chap. An introduction to key distributions and models for epidemiology using R

K A Garrett, P D Esker, A H Sparks

Stevenson, K and M Jeger, APS Press, Minneapolis, MN, "Exercises in Plant Disease Epidemiology", In Press

#### Chap. Cambio climático, enfermedades de las plantas e insectos plaga

K A Garrett, G A Forbes, L Gómez, M A Gonzáles, M Gray, P Skelsey, A H Sparks Jiménez, E, "Cambio clim/'aico y adaptació en el Altiplano boliviano", 2013

#### Chap. Plant pathogens as indicators for climate change

K A Garrett, M Nita, E D De Wolf, L Gomez, A H Sparks

Letcher, T, Elsevier, "Climate Change Indicators", 2009

#### reports

Evaluation of seed treatment for controlling seedling diseases and compatibility with Rhizobium inoculants, 2003.

L J Geisler, A H Sparks

Fungicide and Nematicide Tests 59:ST025

Evaluation of seed treatment fungicides for controlling soybean seedling diseases, 2003

L J Geisler, A H Sparks

Fungicide and Nematicide Tests 59:ST025

### invited talks

2013 Biosecurity Risks in Southeast Asia Impacting on Human Food Supplies

Forum: Pacific Environmental Safety Forum Australian Department of Defence

and U. S. Pacific Command

Sydney, New South Wales, Australia

2010 Global potato late blight risk in response to climate change, possible futures for a

historic disease

Symposium: Emerging Infectious Diseases in Response to Climate Change.

New York Academy of Sciences, New York, New York

# extramural support

2013-2017 **PRISM** Philippine Rice Information SysteM \$2,765,783

Component B – Crop Health Monitoring, Co-PI: A Nelson

2013-2015 **Syngenta** \$454,640

Phase II, Project 2 - Crop Health Management

# professional certifications

PRINCE2 Foundation (2014) candidate number: P2R/009385 - HiLogic Pty Ltd.

# professional affiliations

American Phytopathological Society (APS)

Australasian Plant Pathology Society (APPS)

International Society of Plant Pathology (ISPP)

International Association for the Plant Protection Sciences (IAPPS)